In this video, we'll be talking about arrays, how to create an access arrays, and how to
iterate over arrays.
Arrays are a way to store multiple pieces of the same kind of data.
When you're working with an array, the data is stored consecutively in an array of data.
Each piece of data in the array is called an element.
To access items in the array, an array index is used.
The index always starts at zero, meaning zero items from the array start.
The zero index is simply multiplied by the size of the items.
So at index zero, you're accessing the very beginning, and index one, you're multiplying
the size of the item by one, meaning you skip over the very first item, ending up on
item two.
So zero is item one, one is item two, et cetera.
Lastly, arrays are a fixed size and cannot be resized.
Go does provide facilities, however, to work with arrays of different sizes, and we'll
be taking a look at those in a future video.
So here's a visualization of an array in memory.
If we have this structure right here, a discount card structure, having a ID, store code,
and a rate, this is what it would look like in memory.
So here we have blocks of memory, and the ID takes up two bytes here.
The store code takes up one byte, and the rate takes up four bytes.
This entire chunk here is one discount card structure.
And when you put them into an array, you'll have one here, one here, and one here.
So when we're dealing with array indexes, we have index zero, which is zero bytes from the
beginning.
So it starts right here.
And each one of these discount cards is seven bytes.
So if we want to access item number three, we have to use index two.
So it'll take seven bytes, multiply it by two, which is 14, and it's going to skip over
14 bytes, and you'll end up exactly at your item number three by using index number
two.
So this top one is how it looks in memory, and you can also visualize it like this.
So here we have the item zero, one, two, three, four.
It's the same thing, just a different way to visualize it.
So to create an array, we use the var keyword followed by the name of the array, we have square
braces, the number of items that we want within our array, and the type of the items that
are going to be in the array.
So this first example is uninitialized.
So we'll have an array of three integers, and they'll all be equal to zero.
In this second example, we're using the create an assign, we're using the square braces
to make an array, and again, we're making three integers, and we use curly braces to set
the initial values for these integers.
So we're going to have three integers, and they're going to be equal to seven, eight,
and nine in that order.
Here on our third example, we're using the create an assign again, square braces for an
array, and three dots.
So what three dots is going to do is these dots are going to look over here and see
how many items you've created, and it's just going to substitute that number here for
you.
So the third way is kind of like the default way you'd want to make an array.
That way, you can easily update the number of items without having to actually worry
about how many what your number is right there.
So this will be three and seven, eight, and nine will be your integers.
And this last one here is again, create an assign, we're actually creating a size for
array containing integers again.
The first ones will be seven, eight, and nine, and the fourth item will be zero.
So the fourth will get a default.
So it's we only supplied three numbers.
So to access array elements, we take the name of the array, my array in this case, we use
the square braces, the index that we want to access in equal sign, and the value that we
want to assign.
So this will be how we assign data.
So these three will assign.
So we can index zero, one, and two will be seven, eight, and nine, just like our previous
slide.
And then here on the bottom, if we want to read some data, we can just take the name of
the array, our square braces, and the index that we want to read.
So really just depends if you want to assign, then your array variable will be on the left
side.
If you want to read, then your array variable will be on the right side.
We can also iterate through an array.
So that just means we're going to go through each item one at a time.
To do so, we use the four loops, since that's our go to loop and go.
And what you'll do is you'll have your array.
So we create one here, we have three elements automatically calculated based on the numbers
supplied.
Here on the bottom, we have our four loop.
We create iteration variable i, assign it to zero.
As long as i is less than this function, we're going to go into the loop body, and then
continue on with our typical plus plus to increment it by one.
So this function here is the length functions, len for short.
And what that does is it goes and calculates how many values are in this array.
So for this particular one, it's going to be three because we have three values in our array.
So whenever you're iterating through arrays, you normally want to use the lin or length
function in order to find out how many you've working with that way you can iterate
through each one.
What we're doing in this loop is we're reading from the array since the arrays on the
right side of the variable, and we're assigning a copy into this item variable.
So when we do this, we're making a copy from this array into item.
We then just print it out.
So it's really important when you're working with arrays that you stick within the bounds
of your array.
That means if you have an array with three items and you try to access a fourth item, then
you're going to get an error.
Let's take a look at a few situations where you get some errors.
This one on the left side, this will be a runtime error.
So here we have an uninitialized array that has a size of three, and all the integers
will be zero.
In our for loop, we're not checking the length of the array here.
We're just saying that, hey, keep looping as long as i's less than 10, and we're trying
to print out my array and then the iteration index.
Now it'll happen here is zero, one, and two, those will all check out, because we have
three items.
Once we get to i equals to four, then the program's going to crash because there's no
data at that point because there's only three in the array.
So this right here is going to be a runtime error, and this is why you'll almost always
want to use the length function as part of your condition check.
On the right hand side here, we'll get a compile time error.
So again, we're just creating an array that has three integers, and we're setting the
first three to be seven, eight, and nine, and then we're setting the fourth value to be
10.
However, there's only three values in the array, not four.
And so you're going to get an error when you try to compile the program, and it's able
to calculate how many are in the array.
And since it's reading all the information in your source code, it knows that at this
point there's only three, and at this point you're trying to access a fourth, and so that's
just going to be a compiler error.
On the left side, it's not able to make that determination ahead of time, so it happens
at runtime.
And I hear on the bottom, we have the same as the above.
So we're just using the assign equals instead of the index directly.
So we're trying to read from the fourth index, which doesn't exist, and that's going
to be compile time error as well.
Let's recap, arrays are a fixed size collection of same type items, arrays are accessed
using an array index.
It is an error to use an index that's outside the bounds of an array.
Array elements can be optionally set during array creation, and any elements that you don't
a set during creation will have a default value assigned.
You can use the LEN function, which is short for length, to get the length of an array
and use it to iterate in a for loop.
You'll almost always want to use this function when you're iterating an array.
That way you don't get any out of bounds errors.